Judson Canfield Papers
Litchfield Historical Society
Judson Canfield Papers
1760-1856
Litchfield Historical Society 7 South Street, P.O. Box 385 Litchfield, CT, 6759 URL: http://www.litchfieldhistoricalsociety.org/archon Email: archivist@litchfieldhistoricalsociety.org Phone: 860-567-4501 Fax: 860-567-3565
Canfield, Judson, 1759-1840
0.21
The papers of Judson Canfield (1759-1840), consisting primarily of legal documents, including agreements, deeds, executions, receipts, statements, and correspondence. The papers also include a small collection of correspondence and writings relating to Walter Ferriss, whose daughter married Canfield's son.
1985-24-0
Scope and Contents
The papers of Judson Canfield (1759-1840), consisting primarily of legal documents, including agreements, deeds, executions, receipts, statements, and correspondence. The papers also include a small collection of correspondence and writings relating to Walter Ferriss, whose daughter married Canfield's son.
Judson Canfield was born in New Milford, Connecticut, January 23, 1759. He was a son of Col. Samuel Canfield (1725-1799), an officer in the Revolutionary army and a member of the Connecticut state legislature, and Elizabeth Judson. Judson Canfield was educated at Yale College, graduating in 1782. His uncle, John Canfield, the first lawyer in Sharon, Conn., died in 1786, and Judson then moved to Sharon and established a successful law practice. Many of his clients conducted business or resided in Dutchess County, New York.
In 1796, Canfield purchased land in the Western Reserve (later Ohio) from the Connecticut Land Co. His holdings would eventually total thousands of acres, including property in present-day Bainbridge, Canfield (which was named for him in 1800), Cleveland, Medina, Newton, and Newton Falls.
Canfield was elected to the Connecticut General Assembly from 1802 to 1809 and elected a State Senator from 1810 to 1815. From 1808 to 1815, he was also an associate judge of the county court for the county of Litchfield. In 1815, he moved to Ohio, devoting himself mainly to farming and disposing of his properties. He died February 5, 1840 in New York City.
In 1786, he married Mabel Ruggles (1761-1844). Their children were Henry Judson, Julia Elvira, Elizabeth Hannah, and Caroline Emma. Henry J. Canfield (1789-1856), graduated from Yale College in 1806, studied at the Litchfield Law School in 1808, and was admitted to the bar in 1810. He moved to Canfield, where he practiced law, farmed, raised sheep, and managed his father's land holdings. In 1825, he married Sally Ruth Ferris ( -1881), the daughter of Walter Ferriss (1768-1806) and Sarah (Sally) Morgan Ferriss (1772-1850). They had two children, Julia Elvira Canfield Ruggles (1826-1857) and Judson Walter Canfield. Walter Ferriss, from Oblong, Dutchess County, N.Y., moved to Charlotte, Vt., in 1792. At first, he concentrated on farming, but in the later 1790s he became a Universalist minister and organized several societies in the vicinity. He was appointed to the Committee of the General Convention in Strafford, Vermont, in 1802. In 1803, Ferris attended the Winchester Convention in New Hampshire as a representative from Hinesburg, Vermont.
All three of Judson and Mabel Ruggles Canfield's daughters attended the Litchfield Female Academy. Julia Elvira (1791-1868) married Samuel Flewwelling of New York City, a prominent banker who purchased land in Ohio from Judson Canfield, members of his family, and others. Elizabeth Hannah (1793-1878) married Frederick Augustus Tallmadge (1784-1869) of Litchfield, son of Col. Benjamin Tallmadge. Frederick was a prominent lawyer in New York City and held elective office. Caroline Emma (1798-1872) married William Mackay of New York City, a New York City commission merchant. William Mackay and Julia Canfield Flewwelling were executors of Judson Canfield's will.
Herman Canfield, brother of Judson Canfield, married Fetia Bostwick. In October, 1805, they settled in Canfield, Ohio.
The papers are arranged in two series. Series 1, Judson Canfield papers, primarily consists of documents related to Canfield's law practice. Most involve matters in and around Sharon, Conn., but there are several documents pertaining to land sales in Ohio. There is an interesting letter from Canfield's niece to her mother in which she describes a party she attended, what she and others wore; and news of her relatives in New York and Nyack, including the Bostwick, Flewwelling, Mackay, Ruggles, and Tallmadge families. Series 2, Walter Ferriss papers, includes two documents relating to his affections for his future wife and letters concerning his religious activities, including a letter he wrote to Universalist minister James Babbitt to explain why Ferriss is unable to comply with Babbitt's pressing invitation to him to go to Essex, Vt.
Arrangement of Materials
The papers are arranged in two series:
1. Judson Canfield papers
2. Walter Ferriss papers
Related Materials
Judson Canfield notebook, court docket, 1798-1800, 1846
Samuel Flewwelling Papers (1799-1868)
John Wright Collection (1715-1853)
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Connecticut Land Company
Family Name:
Canfield family
Genre/Form of Material:
Correspondence; Deeds; Financial records; Legal documents; Poetry; Receipts
Geographic Name:
Sharon (Conn.); Western Reserve (Ohio)
Topical Term:
Ferriss, Walter, 1768-1806; Lawyers -- Connecticut; Woolen and worsted manufacture
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Litchfield Historical Society from Richard J. Hughes on 10/29/1985.
Other Information
This collection was processed with support from the Council on Library and Information Resources (CLIR) and the National Historical Publications and Records Commission (NHPRC).
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Judson Canfield papers, 1760-1856
  Arranged by type and then chronologically.
  - Accounts, 1799 (Folder 1)
    Related to costs incurred in Ohio.
  - Accounts, 1800 (Folder 2)
  - Accounts, circa 1800 (Folder 3)
  - Agreement between Canfield, Henry and Radcliff, Jerry, circa 1805 (Folder 4)
  - Agreement between Kellogg, Isaac & Kellogg and Radcliff, Jerry & Canfield, Judson for the construction of carding machines, 1809 (Folder 5)
  - Agreement between Canfield, Herman and Landon, Nathan for the purchase of property in Ohio, 1813 (Folder 6)
  - Bond, Foster, David and Heath, Bartholomew, 1760 (Folder 7)
  - Bond, Canfield, John, 1776 (Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Hoffman, Nicholas to Canfield, John, 1777 Feb 12 (Folder 9)
    Discusses payments for estates.
  - Correspondence, 1787-1793 (Folder 10)
    - Hoffman, Anthony to Canfield, Judson, 1787 May 19 (Folder 10)
      Hoffman is much in want of funds.
    - Johnston, James to Canfield, Judson, 1788 Jan 18 (Folder 10)
      Mr. Spencer has agreed to settle for service against that writ against him.
    - Smith, John to Canfield, Judson, 1793 Feb 21 (Folder 10)
      Briefly discusses the case of Lloyd v. Bogardus and Dibble.
  - Correspondence, Livingston, J. H. to Canfield, Judson, 1797 Jun 10 (Folder 11)
    Discusses lots that Canfield has sold for him.
  - Correspondence, [?] to Tallmadge, Elizabeth Canfield, circa 1810 (Folder 12)
    Two love poems in different hands.
  - Correspondence, Tucker, Anna Dibble to Canfield, Mabel Ruggles, 1829 Aug 31 (Folder 13)
    News of family and friends, her deep religious feeling.
  - Correspondence, Ruggles, Julia Canfield to Canfield, Sally Ferriss, 1846 Oct 9 (Folder 14)
    Describes a party she attended, what she and others wore; news of her relatives in New York and Nyack, including the Bostwick, Flewwelling, Mackay, Ruggles, and Tallmadge families.
  - Deed, Clark, Joseph to Canfield, Judson for property in Sharon, Conn., 1785 (Folder 15)
  - Deed, Smith, Phineas to Sprague, William for property in Sharon, Conn., 1791 (Folder 16)
  - Deed, Doty, David to Swift, Judah for property in Sharon, Conn., 1793 (Folder 17)
  - Deed, Olmsted, Hezekiah to Smith, Platt for property in Sharon, Conn., 1796 (Folder 18)
  - Deed, Canfield, Herman to Canfield, Samuel; Canfield, Judson; Canfield, Philo; Canfield, Ithamar; Canfield, Asher; and Canfield, Herman; for property in Vermont, 1795 (Folder 19)
  - Deed, Walpot, Tobias to Tobias, Smith for land in Sharon, Conn., 1797 (Folder 20)
  - Deed, Allen, Walter and Barton, Caleb to Smith, Isaac for property in Sharon, Conn., 1800 (Folder 21)
  - Deed, Canfield, Samuel to Canfield, Judson for property in Sharon, Conn., 1804 (Folder 22)
  - Deed, Trustees of the Connecticut Land Co. to Johnston, James for property in Ohio, 1807 (Folder 23)
    1831 copy.
  - Deed and indentures, Winans, David and Husted, Derick to Canfield, Judson for property in New York, 1810-1812 (Folder 24)
  - Deed, Canfield, Henry to Canfield, Judson W. for property in Ohio, 1856 (Folder 25)
  - Executions, 1786-1796 (Folder 26)
  - Executions, 1798-1803 (Folder 27)
  - Executions, 1808-1812 (Folder 28)
  - Indenture between Selkrig, William; Selkrig, Jeremiah; and Canfield, Judson, 1812 (Folder 29)
    Regarding 16-year-old William Selkrig's service in a woolen factory.
  - Lease, Steel, Matthew to Canfield, Judson for property in Cornwall, Conn., 1801 (Folder 30)
  - Notes, 1787, 1814 (Folder 31)
  - Orders, 1776-1789 (Folder 32)
  - Receipts, 1766-1774 (Folder 33)
  - Receipts, 1776-1785 (Folder 34)
  - Receipts, 1787 (Folder 35)
  - Receipts, 1788-1789 (Folder 36)
  - Receipts, 1788-1790 (Folder 37)
  - Receipts, 1791-1792 (Folder 38)
  - Receipts, 1793-1797 (Folder 39)
  - Statements, 1774-1787 (Folder 40)
  - Statements, 1788-1789 (Folder 41)
  - Statements, 1786-1793 (Folder 42)
- Walter Ferriss papers, 1789-1803
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Ferriss, Walter to "Madam" [Ferriss, Sarah Morgan], 1789 Apr (Folder 1)
    Ferriss proposes that since he "cannot be favored as your lover I may in future be so much respected by you as to be reckoned amongst the number of your friends."
  - Writings [Ferriss, Walter], circa 1790 (Folder 2)
    - Newton's Analysis of the Revelation (Folder 2)
    - [Sermon?] (Folder 2)
  - "Verses on viewing a lock of Ethelga's hair," Ferriss, Walter, 1792 Sep (Folder 3)
  - Howland, William to Ferriss, Walter, 1797 Sep 21 (Folder 4)
    Howland writes from Oblong, Dutchess County, New York about his religious convictions, Quakers and the Universalist doctrine, and Walter's brother Edwin.
  - Ferriss, Walter to Babbitt, James, 1803 Mar 25 (Folder 5)
    Ferriss explains to Universalist minister Babbitt why he is unable to comply with Babbitt's pressing invitation to him to go to Essex, Vt. Ferriss provides three reasons, one that relates to church regulations and two that are personal.